okay so
today we're discussing a
lecture that um john did at some
university i'm not sure which
um after watching it myself
and trying to make notes it just sort of
well my orientation was to try and make
it super relevant to rip now
or the general project but a lot of it
sort of
just seemed like general facts about how
you know how the mind works and stuff
so i sort of had some trouble making it
i know as relevant as i wanted it to be
to rip now so i'm hoping everybody else
has got better notes than me basically
and just for the people who are
listening to this later what's the name
of the video
uh one second
it's the meaning crisis religion and
religion in the 21st century by john
becky yeah and when i upload this to
youtube i'll i'll put a link
to it in the show notes yeah
um so yeah if anyone else wants to start
with
their notes i'd be grateful
i um i do have a thought i'd like to put
on the table
uh just to kick us off perhaps i found
it very very relevant
uh like i'm first just a disclaimer
um i only got through about
i would say three quarters of the video
um
so i haven't completely finished
watching it um but one thing that really
really stood out for me was
this idea of how the processes
that afford us intelligence have
a built-in tendency
for self-deception and the relationship
to religion that's on a religion for me
is how in community
they might be or there is
other ways that we
process information make decisions do
problem solving
a different form of intelligence that
can help us counteract self-deception
and for me i think that's something
that's very relevant to religion that's
not a religion
yeah we've sort of discussed well john's
definitely discussed
about collective rationality and yeah
that's basically the reason that
collective rationality's
so important well one of the main
reasons is because um
yeah like we all we're all biased but
all of our biases aren't the same
so we can help to correct each other's
bias and thereby
reduce the bias reduce
a certain amount of bias that we could
not produce by ourselves
and yeah i'm not sure on the specific
fix of how we'd set things up on that
planets
and i think it was the 13th
episode of the awakening from the
meaning crisis videos
he talked about reciprocal narrowing
and the opposite reciprocal opening as
being the path to enlightenment
as uh talked about by the buddha
so um i guess it's kind of
it's kind of relevant to retina in that
the reciprocal narrowing
is what we're trying to avoid or prevent
yeah and the reciprocal opening that we
want to achieve right
which i think is is interesting to me
that if
the idea of intelligence can somehow be
transformed from our current way of
thinking about it in in
mainstream society and culture and
that's where for me especially the idea
of religion that's another religion
comes in it's because of
this shared understanding the shared
vocabulary outside of it
if we can understand and define
intelligence differently than we do
currently today
in today's meaning crisis um i think it
will
help create much better affordance to
tap into the mechanisms we can use to
counteract
not only counteract self-deception but
have effective ways of leveraging
each other's intelligence right or the
collective intelligence
or collective rationality i guess you
could say but more than that for me for
me it's
rationality is uh it may be a partner of
intelligence
or a component of it but it's or you
know it has a relationship with
intelligence but it's not intelligence
itself in a way yeah i like the
definition where rationality is
where your your intelligence um
is how you learn and you then when your
intelligence is learning about your
intelligence
to improve itself that's rationality
um yeah i'm gonna paste uh
if that's well maybe let me just read it
and then you can tell me if it's okay if
i paste it in the chat
just to keep it in front of us but uh
the quote directly out of the videos
intelligence is about problem solving
and rationality is about trying to
overcome the self-deception that emerges
out of your attempts to solve your
problems
oh yeah i don't think i write this down
but i thought of um
the phrase that i feel like puts that um
it reveals what i sort of just said
which was uh
so yeah intelligence is problem solving
and then rationality is solving the
problem of problems so
the problems of problem solving
ah that makes sense
so in terms of the the video
the video's relationship with religion
that's not a religion
you mentioned at the start of the
session that
the reason you wanted to use the video
was to to look at how to apply it in
this context of religion that's not a
religion right
can you elaborate a little bit more of
it of what your
intuition was about the value
oh um so are you sort of asking me why i
picked this video
yeah um because it was the second video
in the written our playlist on
john's channel and we're going through
that that's literally the only reason
i picked it that's that's
what we're doing we're going through
each video every two weeks
okay so so in terms of
written r and and improving
self-deception
i guess you know i can see it coming in
in terms of psycho technologies that
help
teach people to better
navigate through self-deception
and maybe classes for example
you know if there's a sunday school type
type situation of
you know on on different techniques of
of controlling for one's own bias or
helping each other control
for bias you know logical fallacies and
the like
can i jump in here guys of course
thank you um i'm picking up a bit on the
uh the bias side which was mentioned
earlier sorry there's a few threads
going
i've got to be quick but um
my understanding from looking at john's
cognitive science course on the
youtube channel is that
bias is from the science point of view
linked
to heuristics yeah
so using heuristics like shortcuts
mental shortcuts
to or rules oh sorry not rules really
it's um
[Music]
well let's say shortcuts like max rules
rules of thumb that's great um which is
great it helps you
solve a problem but he's saying that
intrinsic to that is
the heuristic's are freighted with
biases
so you get the shortcut you get to where
you're going but
you will then be subject to
uh getting a bit trapped by some sort of
bias
which is why he emphasizes you know
learning those cognitive biases etc
but he's putting that in the bigger
frame of
um heuristics as one approach to
problem solving going back to what i
think
velocin said about intelligence i think
that was you velocin sorry
um and then the other way of looking at
intelligence is that logical inferential
way so he seems to have those two big
categories
and plays them off against each other
and then something else emerges
in between which he's calling relevance
realization
and that's intelligence sorry i'm i'm
being a bit general guys but
hopefully that's adding something
you definitely added something because
you basically have
you've basically elucidated one of well
maybe the main way in which intel
like the things that make us intelligent
also make us
foolish like right that it just is
how it works probably most of the time
i'd say
yeah that's interesting
all right so so we're subject as people
to a whole slew of cognitive biases
and these cognitive biases are pretty
well
baked in so so they're they're really
hard to get rid of
but but they can be controlled at least
to some extent you know by
by applying certain techniques so so i
mean for example you know meditation can
help
uh you know insight meditation and
contemplative meditation can help
with creating the proper frame you know
can help help with
with with frame making and frame
breaking
uh you know biases related to how we
treat one another
can be addressed with things like d
logos you know so the bias
you know often you know discussions you
know we have
self-deception with how we view the
other person and the dialogue
psycho technology can help can help
address
you know help make us better at putting
ourselves in the other person's shoes
help really help us really listen to
them not talk past one another
and so on um you know what so we could
you know you could have other exercises
again
develop at assessing the proper frame
because you know we get we have biases
where we zero in on one perspective
and we don't see the other perspectives
and and we're not using we just
get come too attached so so we could so
so we we could identify just
a bunch of these ways we
self-deceive and then figure out
what psychotechnologies we can use to
help us
get better at controlling for them
i guess here's a this sort of maybe
that's a project
if anyone is or wants to be familiar
with
the cognitive biases we could
try and work out like more day-to-day
real-life
examples of where the biases actually
make a difference to people's lives
so i can imagine people hearing about
all these cognitive biases and it just
being like
okay well i'm not a scientist so what
does it matter
yeah and there's another problem that
people think and you know i
i've spent a fair amount of time saying
the skeptic community
and you know the skeptic slash atheist
community where people think just
knowing about psych about cognitive
biases is enough
not to be subject to them and that's
just patently untrue
you know you know i mean knowing about
them helps i mean don't get me wrong
you know knowing the list of the
different types of cognitive biases
is very helpful and that gives you an
edge over someone who's never seen them
but it is not enough on its own just to
know about
these cognitive biases if you're not
actively applying methods
to help counter them then you're
probably succumbing to them
it's the third party effects right so
you um
that's a effect known in psychology and
you can
know that oh a lot so many lots
of marriages will end in divorce that
you never apply it to yourself
you you can know that um oh if you if
you smoke there's a very high chance
you'll apply
you'll die of lung cancer i know there's
a high chance
that you'll die of lung cancer but i
don't think that i'll die of lung cancer
yeah the cognitive bias is always in
one's neighbor's eye
yeah so that's called it's called the
third party effect and it's basically
other people are subject to this but i'm
not because i know about it
that's that's really interesting that
exchange
you just had can can i just make a
comment there
um the reason is because uh sorry is it
shiver any yeah hi hi
uh the reason it's interesting is while
you and veloskin were interacting i was
reading
through the cognitive bias book that
john's got us doing in the
sanger uh and
it sort of strikes a midpoint between
what we've been talking about
in that i i don't find the cognitive
biases very wet
as i find them a bit dry
and so as i'm sort of doing the
discipline i find myself
translating the dryness with a maxim
again so let me just give you
an example in this book okay it's called
cognitive biases a pocket reference book
and i just saw veloskin doing just what
i was doing
so there's this one called loss aversion
and they they have a sentence
loss of aversion is the brain's tendency
to prefer
avoiding losses as compared to receiving
gains
that is the stronger effect of loss on
emotions versus gain
and i just wrote a note that's the glass
half empty
so do you see it as half empty or half
full
and i think veloskin was doing a bit of
a reference to jesus before
is that right yeah
yeah so think so it seems as though
to bridge the gap going to brett's point
cognitive biases are actually proverbs
proverbs um maxims
anyway well i i think what you're saying
is we can use the psychotechnology
that we've been just doing through the
wisdom of hypatia of
of coming up with maxims and memorizing
them
and to choose maxims around the
cognitive biases
to help keep them in mind because that
is an important that is an important
part of
of controlling for biases is is being
able to identify them and keep them in
mind
so coming up with pithy statements to
help you remember to look out for these
biases in your own and others thinking
uh would be would be a helpful
psychotechnology
or an application of the i'm is it
epicurean
i'm forgetting i'm forgetting which one
it's related to but uh you know it's
part of what we're doing now
yes it's epicurus uh maxims so you
remember how
john was saying the epicureans carved to
the maxims into their houses
and stuck them onto their cups like a
post-it note
almost right so this is one way that
that psychotechnology can be applied to
cognitive biases
yes i think so i mean i i don't walk
around saying oh i'm i'm
i'm um i'm doing the anchoring bias
right now
right like like like i see
like i see uh psychotechnologies is a
huge part of retina
like so that's that's i think that's a
major focus that has to be a major focus
in any
kind of written our discussion
on these type of things is what psycho
technologies can we bring
to that task and this is what manuel and
and mark have been working on this as
well in terms of classifying
these psycho technologies into different
different
things that they can afford
so um i i personally
use maxims and the such
as a heuristic psychotechnology in my
day-to-day life
i've developed a a system of of
principle
a principled structure of like
categorical concepts
that i've reduced to simple phrases that
i can relate to any
circumstance i'm in but are context
specific to
emphasize certain circumstance and the
very first one
is i am the only problem that i've ever
had
and i use it as my foundational entry
into into any moment of problem
formulation because i'm grounding it
upon what i consider to be two basic
components of being alive and that is
what john highlights as
the having mode and the being mode
or the becoming mode both of these are
processes of problem formulation
goal orientation operations functions
etc etc
that in my recognition of i am the only
problem i've ever had and recognizing
that
merely the fact of me being alive
necessitates problem in my life
that all of life is in effect some
semblance of tool
or problem and so i don't want to go on
too far
into the details of the specificity i
just wanted to bring up that i
i personally use that great effect and i
think it's very thankful
great that's a good way to avoid
self-deception
fire logic yeah it has helped me quite a
bit
actually um because the blame finger
takes away
accountability and accountability takes
away self-control self-empowerment
uh capacity to respond the stimulus
in an effective way and uh
that's help kept me yes very honest
in a sense it does does tie it back into
velocity and too
which is how he was saying the jesus
quote
uh what is it um it's like you
see the splinter in your neighbor's eye
but you do not see the log in your own
or whatever yes that's brilliant
and so that's a bit what biologic is
doing there
absolutely and
i i just believe it's very important for
just any individual to to find a uh a
relationship with what could be
considered general truths
of this nature because it's just a like
a one-stage
filter to anxiety and distress in the
moment
as long as they have a relationship with
it so speaking they can invoke it
and have an effect which is a practice
having a load of maxims would certainly
go well with trying to create a kind of
retinal culture
because we'd all be kitten into each
other all the time
but like i mean you know
the the moment something becomes a
cliche
it it gets this value judgment right
where it's it's ignored it's like this
idea of i know the maxim therefore
i um i'm good at applying it or
embodying it which is
obviously another cognitive bias right
yeah i'd agree you might say oh yes i
know this maxim i know this maxim i know
what it means
but that doesn't mean you're doing it
same way people know that they're meant
to drive at the speed limit
i think this is where uh something
that's a feature of
some religions is
quite interesting is where they have
ceremonies or celebrations
uh where it's about
savoring the meaning of even if it's
symbolic meaning of metaphoric meaning
of let's say certain maxims right
and it could be an enacted maxim not
necessarily
you know one that's just a bunch of like
you know
like a proverbial phrase um
and and that can counteract this effect
of saying oh something just becomes a
cliche
because you you know it's not about
recognizing oh i'm familiar with the
maxim but it's about
um making sure that one has a first-hand
experience of what it
means to embody the maxim
and that's how things like ceremonies
rituals those types of things can be
can perhaps be very powerful yeah
even more than that right you have to
have an embodied sense of development
right like just having a rule somewhere
right like
in in in fancy colors and with a picture
next to it
it's not going to help it right it's
just a rule right you need you need to
get there right you need to
see why the rule is important it's it's
not used just to have the rule
that's interesting it makes me think of
how john quotes harry frankfurt and
talks about bullshit
and how we have to learn how to not
bullshit ourselves
and how that might be something to watch
out for with maxims
so i'm sorry
please go ahead uh i well i
want to agree with everything that's
been said but i also want to just put
forth an additional
psych technology that i that i utilize
in that specific maxim previously
because maybe this might spark something
useful
is that i have an actual device that um
that i attach to my wrist and that
interacts with my hand
that creates a problem in my life and in
the wearing of it
i have to i have i have these rules that
i notice immediately if i'm not
following because i'm not adhering to
this because this thing becomes a
problem it starts getting caught
getting in the way and there's it's a
wheel of metal on the end
of a paracord so i have to adapt
to this additional element of
articulation in the freedoms of my body
that is constantly occurring on this
this pre-attentive level
because if i'm wearing it throughout my
day i've just added an intentional
problem to my life i have reformulated
the problem of self to have an
additional freedom
of enactment that i must adapt to and as
i build rules of adaptation
these must adapt to the pockets of the
moment if i want to use this hand
i not only have to mitigate the problem
but i have to find a way to mitigate the
problem in such a way that it
develops a harmonic with the way that my
hand can grasp
object and engage with my life so
i i just i guess my point here is kind
of in the ecology of practice point of
view
which i believe is very uh religion
that's not a religion
oriented is that all of these approaches
must be constant in a certain sense to
uh to address
what john is referencing by um
self-deception and relevance realization
and insight
that that there's there are fatal flaws
in each individual
approach period and
it's it's i mean am i wrong in the
assumption that the goal here is to
find very specific psych technologies
that can
access all of the part of a person so to
speak
and then to formulate an ecology so that
people can
um get it all the parts they can't even
see so to speak
in communal expression
but that's the end goal no i i think
the goal is at least where i am marker
going
with with this and with the
schematization that we're trying to do
is we're trying to generate certain
affordances with
a certain practice right so if you're
right we don't have to fix everything
right we cannot fix everything
people run into problems in their lives
and they need fixes for the problem so
what you want to do is you want to have
a way to
recognize where your problem is in an
efficient way and then
find a way to deal with it that's
adhering to your personality and your
specific situation
in relation to time and attention and
all that stuff right
that's where i'm working at least we
want to fix the problem itself then
so to speak the the intrinsic problems
that
impede our decision-making process and
our developmental growth
no perennial we don't want to fix
anything we want to give people the
opportunity to fix
themselves we want to give them the
tools that they need
to grow as people basically
no okay so the fix is the wrong term um
but the goal here is still to provide
means of resolution which in and of
itself is a resolution of a problem
yeah sort of um i think use the right
word
we're trying to we've got a load of
perennial problems we're trying to
cope with them like we're trying to be
better but
the word people have a problem with the
word fix i think because it's
it's got this very discreet sense of oh
i fixed it now and that's it but that
i concur i i i concur it was a poor term
for the circle no no it's no problem
it's just uh
yeah that's why people might object
yeah and coping by contrast suggests a
more ongoing thing
yeah and i think uh john is dead set
against that from what i've
understood i think he even
uh in a very knowing way talks about
being against
quote the final solution
so i prefer
i prefer the term resolution myself
yeah i think the point is going into the
whole
ways of knowing that um
it's a very propositional way of looking
at things if you
say i'm gonna fix it whereas
if we went down to the other end it's a
much more participatory way of looking
at by saying
i'm in a process of of addressing it
and yeah we really want to break out of
that
yeah it's an important distinction we're
not saying
come come to us and we'll fix your
problems we're not fixing your problems
what we're saying is come to us and we
will teach you strategies that you can
use
to deal with your problems in an
everyday in everyday life
to find meaning in your life yes
tools of use are being offered
that's yes we're not solving problems
we're solving the problem
of problem solving basically
which is essentially my original point
about that it's still it's still the
same thing
like in the end when you get down to
that but it's decentralized
it's specific sorry ronnie we're getting
a little background noise
right at this point like i said i think
with um the
we're still doing a lot of work on
defining okay
what problems we're looking at solving
so that's why we've got the list of the
um perennial problems and perennial
needs and
um i think we've got someone working on
a list of uh
drives and motivations as well
is that right
i think that's um manas
we're talking about um the values
now are those things that you can
extract from this video we just watched
very specific
specifically no those things from that
video now
okay
if you have a look well say non-linearly
then just in the way
that self-deception can
cascade into more specific problems
that's relevant to the values
okay what i would say there at least
from my thinking so far in working on
the values is the problem is that of
what that is taught in the video of
heuristics with
that risk of bias right so in the
written or
next channel i posted some examples of
just trying to figure out if you know
for lack of a better way to put it the
structure of values
and um perhaps a better way to word it
is to say the heuristic
of values
for example it's good self-preservation
is a good value
if you can take care of yourself well
that has a lot of benefits
you can be a productive member of a
community but what happens when the
community is under serious threat
then the opposite of self-preservation
starts becoming an affordable
value which is self-sacrifice right like
the the warrior archetype and saying
i'm gonna fight for the survival of my
collective
um as an example and and those two
things are polar opposites
on a bias or should we say heuristic
of what is the appropriate thing to do
or what is the
uh quote-unquote right thing to do what
is the relevant thing to do
and that's what i think makes right now
what makes values kind of a little bit
fun
to play with and work with because it's
not the values themselves
that feels like it's meaningful it's
really
space that values live in if i can put
it like that you know the space of
heuristics
and yeah this is virtues like why why
are we talking about values or not
virtues
is there a distinction i was going to
say like
what you're you called the values in
that thing you posted
like it's just a it's literally a virtue
like you you
you're describing aristotelian style
virtue
where it's uh finding the relevant spot
between the
extremes so i'm
absolutely open for updating my how
should i say
the way that i'd uh the kind of
vocabulary that i'm using the
definitions and stuff but
the reason i want to shy away from the
idea of virtue is because
i want to make space for
for a lack of a better way of saying the
dark side of means because it has a
space right because of the bias
because of context now one might argue
that but that's
what virtue does it already brings that
context
into being but um i think there's a
little bit
of stereotype of stigma when you talk
about virtue right there's this
archetype of the the good and the light
and the you know the hero archetype
right not
as opposed to let's say the renegade you
know or the rebel
um which also has a place right and and
i'm feeling like
if i perhaps if i stay away from that
uh maybe just my subjective meaning that
i'm that i'm
linking to to virtue if i try and stay
away from that i can make space
for a more comprehensive view of values
or whatever
of course thank you thank you um
in the virtue framework uh there's not
an opposite but there's uh
there are two poles of vice right with
your values nomenclature
what is the alternative
i think that's where i i probably need
to update my vocabulary and do some more
homework and research
um i literally jumped into this
completely blind so i really appreciate
the feedback for saying
this you know i should probably
look at the model of virtues instead i
mean i agree that values is different
than virtues because sometimes the
things you value aren't
necessarily a virtue so if
if i value time time spent alone
that's not a virtue it's something i
value and it's something which i'll
spend
effort to get but it's not not
necessarily a
good value
well spending time alone could be a
virtue if you're an astronomer
but it sounds to me like like what manos
is trying to get at
is that um a value can be good or bad
but a virtue just implies that it's good
exactly talking about values is a good
way to actually look at this
the positive connotation to it which
value doesn't
yeah what a virtue can be like a virtue
uh can be double-edged or verges can
hence the golden mean i'm not sure what
the
exactly
is really useful for the point that
menace was trying to make sorry
yeah i do want to encourage you man it's
not meant to be challenging but
encouraging
um like even to work with your
proposition
maybe the opposite is something called
an unvalue i don't know
it wasn't nitpicking it just happens to
be true that's why
morals and virtue ethics are so
notoriously fraught
well if the op the opposite is something
you'd value is
something that's worthless for you
wow there's i guess there's a there's
the opposite in the terms of
worthlessness but then there's like
this value where you like i val
i value for the sake of argument i value
happiness
but i dis value suffering but i find
you know things that make no difference
worthless
i think one of the things that i like
about the idea of values as opposed to
virtues
is that the idea of value has this
component of it
that's about motivation
whereas virtue does not virtue is more
like a
idealized goal state or embodiment of an
idea not necessarily
the sense of being like
motiva it doesn't have the dimension of
motivation behind it so it feels like
it's a little bit removed from
um okay i just want to reset the frame
because
if we're talking about this in the
context of written or like
how do like values seem to be
personal and thereby irrelevant well
well there's two ways we can look at
that so so one is
we could say part of written r would be
cultivating virtue
you know for example john's structure
the dialogues exercise
you know the the actual exercise of
dialogue is to focus on
uh talking about virtues and you know
one of the goals of that is to help
promote virtues in our lives in terms of
value
i think what ritner wants to do is help
cultiva so that's cultivating relevance
realization
and and it's helping us
pick the right values the best values
the most relevant values
to value and that's right yeah
by the way what man i think what mannis
is um
what one of the words i use to describe
what i think manus is
researching is like temperaments so
like my temperament is very solitary and
then there'll be someone who's
got a temperament where they always want
to be with other people
obviously that's just like a temperament
but the virtue would be when you're
you're
seeing these two temperaments and you're
finding the right
place between them so it's
like the value is like i i've i
value um solitude
in that sense but then um
virtue is more normative right
yeah can i pick up on that too sorry
after you go ahead that's right i just
did it
i i did want to feed into that because
again it's there's
there's sort of a midway point which is
uh you were talking about temperament
veloskin just now and manus is looking
at temperament
and uh there's there's someone else
talking about aristotle
i'm not sure who but as i understood it
aristotle is calling a virtue a
disposition
it you know some people call it an
excellence and excellence of the soul
etc etc but it's also i think in greek
it's hexist
which means a disposition which might
also be considered a temperament
uh just throwing that in there we need
to
perhaps just move away from discussing
and and this is by no means a criticism
of the discussion that's happening it's
very useful and valuable and insightful
but i just want to avoid the problem of
going back
and forth on semantics and be clear on
the meaning of what was done and i think
that's why some people were saying
this is what i mean with virgin this is
what you mean with virtue and this is
what we
so so just to make it clear what i mean
with
values um is kind of
um recognizing this process
of cultivating virtues right um and
for for example um something that's part
of being human
is uh one way of looking at dealing with
our problems and getting out of you know
getting unstuck
is becoming aware of let's say for
example shadow archetypes
right like ways we behave like for
example behaving like a victim
or behaving like a child so the victim
is like you know i'm
powerless you know i'm i'm the victim of
something outside of myself right the
child is uh
not accepting responsibility or or
anything like that as an example
um so what happens is they've got pay
payoffs
right so uh let's let's look at the
um i want to use an easy example with
the shadow archetype of the
of the idea of the prostitute and the
idea of the procedure to say is like
okay there's something that doesn't uh
that
that isn't aligned with my values or my
integrity or the way i would i would
prefer to do things in a very you know
in a way that's aligned with
with who i see myself as my my values my
virtues my identity
but i'm going to do but i'm going to do
it because there's
uh a practicality or pragmatic side of
it for example
um i personally work in an i.t job right
but i hate working an i.t job i don't
find it meaningful at all
but it pays well right so in a sense
what i'm doing is
i'm prostituting myself in that sense as
a shadow archetype right
now what is the value that comes out of
that for me the value that
and it's about being responsible
financially responsible
right but now if i want to get unstuck
and i'll go to the next level and say i
want to make a living out
by living out of integrity with what i
really do deeply
care about and i'm passionate about
that's the next step so what
the idea of values for uh does in this
sense
it helps me build a story from where i'm
stuck to where i'm going and builds
empathy
so when two people are having a
conversation with each other
it can create help create that
transformation that that
that process and for me that's what i
mean with well that's my goal with
trying to stick around this world and
this semantics of values as opposed to
others i hope that's helpful yeah so
just to put that in context and first
sorry chevron we're getting a lot of
background noise are you able to mute
when you're not
talking yeah no problem um
so just to put into the context of
written r um
i i think what we should be focusing on
is okay
you know you have we have that process
there that you just described
how do we structure that uh
to help people figure out their own
values
uh you know their own relevant values
and you know like what
i i well i guess i want to hear from you
guys but i think
we're tr we want to keep this
conversation
in the frame of what do we want to
integrate into written or what do we see
as possibly
being a part of retina rather than
getting into the individual examples of
positive virtues and values and and so
on
can i ask a meta level question and and
point to the present moment and ask what
everyone's values are in the present
moment
and the attempt to create this this
discussion
and further the religion that's not a
religion
what values are you bringing currently
or what virtues are you looking for
currently to
to do this process in conversation
my immediate thought is that that's such
the answer to that would be so vast that
i cannot even
begin to answer that feels like there's
just so many values operating at once
that it's
it's not very easy to even say it
well um why should we listen to you
velocity
let me ask that because i might have a
good idea
think to tyler's question just to be
helpful
my value is encouragement to trying to
look for the good in what other people
are saying
trying to seek to learn so that
something grows
beautiful once a minus contextualization
is to help bring a certain perspective
on things
to see what value we can get out of the
content
yeah one of the values i'm trying to
bring here is to focus on
written our specific and what what we
want to
get from it rather than you know so
staying on topic i guess uh
or in the right frame in context
i'm at rats
so if we were to stay on topic where did
we wind up
well the idea is that we don't know that
but it's
probably going to be helpful what i
i see these sessions as brainstorming
sessions and uh
of you know you know wisdom the crowds
getting a lot of ideas
thrown out and hopefully then narrowing
them down to the best ideas
and proceeding with that so
the values that are discussed and the
topics
either are going be in agreement with
what we already have within us
or uh disagreement right
no it's not about what we have within us
like
it's an external project right like we
need
you want to facilitate something in the
world right so and and something can be
useful to that facilitation or it cannot
be
right so i don't i don't think it has
anything to do with what it might be one
step further though
you're hoping it to be useful in what
regard
for the informing of our actions or our
perspectives
well we're not there yet like that's not
relevant
it's kind of building creating the
building blocks to get there though
right
i mean in this specific context in this
moment in this video in this discussion
um the golden thread i see pulling
through is one of the things that's
talked about in the video
is the theme of self-deception the value
of
and and it's interesting to me that you
know as a
as a collective of the participants here
it was brought up this idea of talking
about that implements the values the
virtues
and i think how those two things are
connected for me at least
is to use the idea of understanding
and recognizing um
the mechanics of values and the you know
how they work
as a way to deal with self-deception as
a way to get out of that
um
that's not how most people operate in
the world
well that's the point of retinol right
it's it's to
provide an alternative to the way most
people do things in the world so that
they can make progress
no no no no like people no
like people don't have the capabilities
you're requiring from them
so if you if you want to build a system
on that level
that's just gonna fail i beg to differ i
mean i think
my personal experience um in therapy as
a patient
is um that's kind of what happens it's
the stepping stone effect
yeah you're really smart and other
people are not that smart
that's that's built into the process of
what the therapist is using is
is giving uh out of a place of empathy
a place for these different values that
can come up so instead of a person
feeling
let's say judged or they feel wrong or
they feel
they're missing something or they have
to you know like this artificial side of
it which will not bring transformation
there's this um it's like a
like building salience in this
transformative process
by recognizing through empathy the
different can i
can i for example use the term the
payoffs that
uh unhealthy behavior gives and say oh
that's why i'm doing it and it helps get
to the root of an issue
and it recognizes a value and then that
allows processing to shift from being
parasitic processing
and reciprocal narrowing happening to
you know being able to get a better
handle of those things
and then develop a better tool
personally
to transform um and that's that's my i'm
i'm not disagreeing with that process
and the
possibilities of the process i'm just
saying that that's not
going to work pragmatically
guys because we're not we're not solving
the problems for them
we're giving them the tools so would
that therapy have been as effective
if the person had just said all right
here's all of this information here's
all of these books
go and read them and start figure out
what your problems are
what pitfalls you're falling into and
figure out for yourself what
prop what parasitic processing you're
using and figure out for yourself
how to grade kids
creating tools for people to do that
right
that won't happen people don't do that
say that
i think what are we doing right now
yeah i just want to say that i think
that perhaps we're try we've got a
too narrower view on retina here because
um
the the idea that we're solving problems
or trying to
to cope with problems and everything or
you know trying to build a toolkit to
cope with problems it's all great but
i'm not hearing any communities in any
of that and if britain or isn't
affording communities and i don't see
what it's what good it's going to do
and so i think um
at least something of what manus is
talking about they will have to come
in to the retina project if it's going
to be able to build communities
oh remember we haven't been talking
about we haven't been doing
written our writ large here we've been
talking about
like there was some specific things that
came out of that video such as
reducing self-deception you know
controlling for bias
so that's sort of uh you know and
you know cultivating virtue we that's
why i think the focus has been on
tools for that rather than communitas
which is
i mean maybe there are elements of that
in community tasks but but
but i think we've been talking about a
bit of a narrow focus i'm just
saying and fair enough but
um just because we're talking about the
video doesn't mean that we can just
ignore everything that we're supposed to
achieve and then shoot down
good ideas and say that they're bad
because they're not dealing with this
little one aspect that we're trying to
deal with
because of the video that's my point no
no sure i was just saying
it's not a fault that we're narrowing in
on these tools right now because that's
i think that that's what's most relevant
to the issues that we've been talking
about
i mean yeah i don't know i don't i don't
know problem with any of that and i i
applaud it
as i said um i'm just saying that like
the criticism that manus is receiving
there
isn't justified because i'm i'm not
hearing anything about the communities
and we shouldn't overlook that when
we're talking about well
what are we trying to do with written on
you know like what are we trying to
value when we
when we come into the retinal
discussion because as i say communitize
is definitely one of my values
for sure yes and in the spirit of that
steward
steward or strawn i prefer stream
thanks drew in the spirit of that um
being completely open i don't know what
i think about
religion that is not a religion i'm a
rookie
um so there's a perspective within the
communitas of this conversation
in terms of a frequency some some people
are really deep into it
i'm just interested you know i
don't know exactly where i stand so that
there's
there's an open space as well there's
some
something there as well thank you for
sharing that
yeah no and i appreciate that
perspective though i think for the
purpose of
these sort of committee type meetings i
i think we should
just take you know unless we're going to
have a a talk on just is written our
good
good in itself is just start from the
assumption that yes
we're trying to make a go of written r
or at least explore it
and and and go from there
yeah totally
like like like it's easy in these
conversations to get up on these general
topics of just what is virtue and what
it values but
you know maybe i'll just bring it out to
the group do we want to really just
focus these meetings on
sort of much more pragmatic what would
what would we specifically do what can
we imagine doing in a retina
specifically for these
i things i prefer that level of
conversation as well brett
something that could result in action
not necessarily but you know small
enough stuff
that if we decided to take an action
then we could
maybe we maybe we need to restructure a
little bit and have
one discussion you know macro
level and then play around with
lower levels then back to macro over and
over again well
change scales back and forth we're in
the presence of other people
um this is a bit of a community
in the moment is this
satisfying everyone's desire to be in
communitas
if not what is missing
it's it's not the purpose to be in
communities like let's please get off
that train like i'm
we're here to have a meeting and a
meeting is not for communities right we
can have a different event
and then we can have communities in that
event like
or or rather it like this meeting itself
is not communitas
though we can talk about how in written
are we would cultivate humanitas
right so sure sure right yeah that's a
different
topic yes i agree well that that's what
i was talking about
not the the latter not the former
right i think in general any kind of
stated goal for this meeting would have
helped me
this is my first time um i enjoy being
listened and participate but i'm not
quite sure how yet
well um the the proposal that i was
going to make is that if we're going to
watch a video every other week
then the discussions in the in between
weeks can be the more general ones and
then we can try and use the
the religion that's not a religion
videos
on a weekly basis to try and pick out
more specific things that we can then
comb over to collect for the more
general conversation
by general do you mean less focused or
like
overarching yeah well i mean people are
trying to figure out now you know
how do we approach written or how do we
talk about written or what what should
be on the agenda
you know how do we arrange this all of
those kinds of questions so
presumably if we have that conversation
over a long period of time
we'll start to make progress right and
that'll start to form up written or in a
more general sense or at least we'll get
an idea of how we want to work together
to accomplish that
and so if we have that general
discussion and then we have the
every other week we have the videos then
we can use the videos as a
you know we can kind of mine the
whatever viveki said
to use as inspiration for the more
general conversation
then then we've got the high level and
the low level or the
the details level in the general level
um kind of playing together with each
other in a way that i think could work
so i i just want to make a suggestion
right like if
if people want to like focus on one
specific part
then they can just choose to meet up
right they can make
an event and they can invite people so i
encourage people to do that
and it is it is good to get that
knowledge back into a bigger group
at a specific point so i'm i'm in total
agreement here
yeah i was thinking about a similar line
sorry that we could have with
the you know committee and we have
subcommittees you know subgroups within
the committees who are working on
specific projects and then they can come
back and report to the larger committee
and you know people can be part of as
many subgroups as they want
but we could have focused
focus uh are there agenda items
well does anyone have agenda items
i mean what we've we're doing is uh
we'll come up with a project
that we may wish to have done usually i
i assume mostly
that will happen in these discussions
and then someone can step up if they're
interested to take it on
and then in so this week is a
video week and then next week is like a
homework week
where we bring back what we've sort of
thought about and researched
on our little self-taken project
i have just a general question i mean is
it safe to assume to everyone that
it's everybody's goal to create written
art and
promote it and have it live in the world
is that the shared purpose of everybody
on the call
yeah it's certainly the goal of you know
the written our
interested people yeah it may not be the
goal of everybody
in here but that's why we're sort of
saying
for the purposes of these meetings it
should be the assumed goal
and and again i think under the under
the assumption that we know
we have no idea if it'll work or not but
i think we
the people here believe it's the people
who really want to get involved in this
believe it's a worthwhile project
and want to give it a good it's good a
shot as the as it can of working
so i think that's sort of the that
should be the one the motif for the
motivation the the primary assumption
that we just start from
for for these particular things yeah
thanks for clarifying that because
just coming in um maybe this is useful
feedback but i wasn't sure if
this is more of just an intellectual
pursuit you know part of the larger
understanding of all this material
versus maybe more of a pragmatic attempt
at making something really happen in the
world and i think we can have
meetings you know we could have we could
have discussions like you've just
discussed like hey what's the point of
written r
is it a good idea but i think that's
separate from from this type of thing
the other thing we can do and this is
what i've been thinking of is you know
maybe appointing a chair of this
committee and other committees that
we're starting to form
and the chair can and the chair can
maybe work with the people and take
advice
and then create a an agenda each week
for these
for these meetings so so it can have
sort of a specific focus
what do you guys think of that idea yes
i'd like to answer by still mending two
things quickly
if you might allow me my understanding
is that the agenda for today's meeting
was to discuss
to make notes off from the video and to
see what we can get out of that for
maybe
working projects or you know sharing
insights of what we got out of the video
that's
so that was for me very clear and i also
want to steal man
i think it was joel that mentioned about
uh
just the um intellectual discussion
versus maybe practical things later on
um and just to make sure they'll
understand correctly
asking about not just let's say figuring
stuff out understanding it but also
creating something doing something
that's applicable that's actionable
is is that my understanding of the
question you are asking
in other words let's say if we develop a
tool that is useful for
people that would be a practical as
opposed to only intellectual discussion
yeah or even to take it to like an
extreme let's say that there was
uh already a solution out there is this
the same group of people that would
uh are so motivated they would you know
clean the toilets and mop the floors to
put it out there or is this the group
that would like to stay more into
intellectual realm and be contributed to
the idea space of it
for instance
in other words the framing of retinol
right there
i think it's more that we i think it's
more a question about the way i'm
listening to people
speak to these topics um sounds as
though
they already spend time thinking in a
space so their contribution would be
considered um idea contribution or
you know there's like i'm not sure if
this is like an altruistic group of
people do whatever it takes you know
or they'll do what it takes within their
wheelhouse i guess
so i think i can you go first all right
yeah i think that um this will be
slightly more theoretical
along those along the lines that you've
described
but what we're doing here isn't the only
thing that the server is doing there are
lots of other
practical projects that are ongoing
where people are actually trying to
practice put the stuff into practice
so you get both but the emphasis i think
you will find most people would be more
interested in the
in the idea space but the idea is i
think to
work with the ideas in such a way that
we can develop practices which and then
you would see
in in other places not necessarily in
the written eye discussion anymore
yeah so i think i i want to sort of
recon orient everyone who's here and
interested
so we determined in the first discussion
that we were having troubles
with retina so we had the um
voice disc discussion right and we
determined that
problem formulation was the most
important thing we need to do
and so that's that's what john has
said himself so what we're
we're doing is meeting up to try and
i guess for now is to determine
what perennial problems or
problems we're actually trying to solve
like what's the purpose of retina
exactly and that seems like an
inherently
kind of intellectual endeavor i suppose
so that that that's we're setting up
this sort of very general framework
and we're kind of building down into
uh what what's going to be a bit more
practical
and that helps a lot so i think that
there's a principle here i'm identifying
that is that there won't be like an
orchestration of existing tools and
technologies that emerge
into written r the idea is that there's
some first principles
that may be kind of pushed down to well
to create
an emergent written r from those almost
ab initio creation of this thing
well i mean honestly i'd like
sorry to interrupt um i'd like to
actually say that if that
is the case uh like i'm hoping it's not
then i would like to help change that to
incorporate cooperate things that might
be useful and valuable like for example
one of the basic ideas of the awakening
from the meaning crisis series is
to make use of the existing psycho
technologies
right and move away from the problems
like
dogma for example right of old ways of
thinking so definitely about
i think using what what exists and
what's useful
um i hope i'm understanding
that right from my point of view on on
redneck's intention
yeah so what we're what we determined as
often said
the first discussion was um we don't
have a full
um idea of what problem we're trying to
solve with retina
because it's not just one problem
there's a whole bunch of other problems
so what we're doing is first of all
we're looking at formulating the problem
and getting a clear understanding of
what problem we're trying to solve
at that point we'll say okay so what
existing psychotechnologies do we have
that can help solve this problem and
okay what
rituals do we already have that to help
solve this problem
and what kind of things do we need to
create still so
um if you think about it it's a
multi-step project
the first step is um basically if you if
you think about when you get a group
project
when you're assigned a group project in
a class um and you're told
this is what you need to do we don't
have the this is what we need to do
so we're getting that this is what we
need to do and then we're taking that
and using those aspects to figure out
okay how do we do this what needs doing
what needs
creating what do we already have
and just to point out what someone also
mentioned in the rest of the server
there's a lot of stuff going on where
we're
putting psychotechnologies into practice
and experimenting with rituals
so so we've got we've got the meditate
we've got
we've started with yoga in the morning
and meditation following john's course
we're going
through the wisdom of hypatia now uh we
we've
we've been experimenting with lectio
divina
we're we're going to be moving into uh
dear logos
so we've got a lot of uh we've got a lot
of things going on
where we're we're playing with the
serious play of these
of the psycho technologies for example
that john and others have
have mentioned and uh so
so there's a lot of practical stuff
going on too so i encourage everyone to
to participate in in those because i
think those the ecology of practices
has got to be i think at the heart of
practical written art
and you know like so so in some respects
i see
the activities going on the discord as
written are like
at least a proto-typical written art
like
we're doing we have a sense of how we're
going to come together brett
like what happens when manuel and i
disagree like
strongly on a topic are we going to arm
wrestle it out or
how does this community go the great the
great thing about
yeah the great thing about the approach
that we've been taking
to this and to the ecology of practices
is that
there isn't it's not a dogmatic approach
we want to identify
psychotechnologies that afford certain
certain
you know cultivatory goals
and we don't all have to agree on this
is
this is the one this is the right one so
for example there's a billion different
meditation practices you know if you're
doing a meditation practice and you're
following
a particular school that's that's great
you don't have to follow
john's course or or the other course you
know it
probably we want to have some agreement
you know on
you know writ large that we want to
you know get better at rel relevance
realization but
but we can have different ways of
achieving that and that's
not a bad thing and then hopefully we'll
figure out over time what
what the which techniques psycho
technologies are better and which are
which are not as effective and and some
might be effective for some people and
not for others
i'm actually do that get at your
question
i actually this all helps so much um i
i haven't what i'm hearing or maybe what
i've been proposing even i guess
um from listening to john vervicky's
series so far i'm about three quarters
of the way through
uh there's so many lessons of where
things go wrong
and i'm almost wondering if this group
would be almost like uh trying to
establish a criterion by which you could
just discriminate
what should not be written are or where
it might be perhaps a missing
point or um missing a critical dimension
something like this i like that
formulation that's a good orientation
yeah
welcome phil
hey who's listening and did what i say
get at what you were getting at tyler
or sort of
i do have some
very large questions with regards to
what product it is that we're going to
try to create here at the end of all of
this discussion
right sorry can i can i just stop us
here
because um i've realized we're just sort
of going further and further into this
meta discussion of what we're doing
when that's probably appropriate for
next week
do we want to return to the video
it seems that's like the purpose of this
discussion
like is anyone the video is the purpose
of the discussion
yes
the agenda item is to discuss the video
yeah uh i've got to go veloskin
that that's where i was jumping in to
the conversation
i didn't really have a really strict
understanding of
what's happening in this channel so i
apologize
to you manuel i think you've got a lot
of work going on in particular with
brett and
other people about definitions and so on
so
apologies for anybody wasting time and
so on
no you haven't wasted it in good faith
it's been great no
really i i think it's probably my fault
because i forgot to
put in the announcement that that's what
this was about so
it's mainly my fault for that well i'm
going to keep at it
i really appreciate everyone's spirit
and um
i wish everyone a great day and
hopefully we'll talk again soon myself
so
have a great day see you guys
so i just i just want to clarify the
disagreement with you tyler right
like i'm i'm i'm not against talking
about
social structures or whatever right but
you need to do it at the right
level right you cannot you cannot do it
uh
like what do you want no it's like what
do we need
that's a different different set of
questions oh yeah this is uh
not about the video so can we yeah sure
right i just wanted to clear up
okay so i'm just gonna put this back on
i'm gonna put
put us back on track myself i thought
that there was a really deep relevance
to the to the chessboard analogy
that john described where
um so you've got
this problem that you're meant to solve
which is whether or not
you know you can put the dominoes on the
chessboard and cover every square
without you know having a domino hang
over the edge
but the way to solve it isn't to just
kind of
brute force it but you've kind of got to
step
back and then start thinking about
i'm not sure how to put it has anyone
got any sort of
thoughts transframing it's changing
frame
so
like it is yeah if you think about it in
terms of the even and the odds
or the you know that there's equal
number of blacks and whites on the
on the board yeah so you're just seeing
it in
the same problem in a different frame
and it's only that way that you can
easily come with the
the solution because the other solution
is combinatorially
too explosive like our best computers
i don't know would take years doing it
or something like that
i found that frame that example really
useful uh as uh
in what feels like is happening in the
academy a lot today that you have a lot
of momentum around approaches to ways to
solve complex problems
you know in the sciences and that you
might have this other frame but when you
present that other frame
it might be considered naive if it's not
as
complex and machined kind of and i think
that's a really interesting
point to feel into in terms of
what it would take to these kind of
shifts in perspective to do
better sense making
yeah i was like um i thought like sort
of sort of taking
that or mental orientation
might actually be really helpful for
root now if indeed we're not already
doing it because i'm not sure we're not
already doing it
well yeah because i think one of the
things john has said about that is you
can't just tell people think outside the
box
that apparently doesn't work uh yeah
you have to get them better at shifting
frame
better at zooming in and zooming out
i wonder if you actually ask them
instead of saying think outside the box
we said
where is the box if that might actually
not be more useful in helping people to
get the solution
sorry we'll just just to clarify we're
talking about the nine dot problem if
anyone
doesn't have any idea what we're talking
about i was actually just listening to
episode
i'm pulling up my spotify right now
seven or eight or something i'll know in
a second
and um he was talking about something at
least related to this
where he's saying um that instruction
that's too
harsh and also instruction that's too
ambiguous or both not useful
there is some insight research that has
shown that and i can
put references in the discussion later i
have to look it up
but that do show that there are a
quality of problems or you can teach the
the quality of move it takes to think
outside the mop the box they can teach
insight
through a kind of meta process which i
think is really helpful
that sounds extremely useful to us
because we would definitely want to
incorporate that into right now
well um from speaking from memory john
mentioned there was that used
transcranial magnetic stimulation or
whatever
and they could actually
there's there's like a left hemisphere
to the right hemisphere switch when
insight occurs and they were using the
the magnets to basically stimulate the
same parts of the brain
and when they did that i think you said
the the solution to the mind problem
went from like zero to something like 25
percent
or something crazy so yeah
yeah there's definitely something along
those lines that we've already
can use in in the form of tron what is
the transcript
transform magnetic stimulation
basically they apply strong magnets to
your brain so you're saying we should
just take magnets and just put it in our
head all the time
yeah that's probably micro technology
yours for only 99.99
murphy's laws of combat if it's stupid
but it works it isn't stupid
[Laughter]
so we basically hook people up to the
trans training stimulation machine
and then we go okay think about one of
your problems and then we just
stimulate them no no yeah exactly
i guess we've just got our ecology
practices now
[Music]
who was talking about it beforehand yeah
i'll post that i'll post that's a
discussion fred
thank you very much
so so so velocity so so just to guide us
in how you wanted to take about this
discussion so
we have this issue you know of
transframing
and the you know whether it's a nine dot
problem or the checkerboard
the chessboard problem how how should we
deal with that in this meeting
see that's the thing i don't know it was
just it
it occurred to me like the way that
works
because it feels like a lot of the time
even when we're
actually problem formulating if
i get the sense even i am just sort of
butting my head against the problem a
little bit
because there is a combinatorially
infinite number of ways
like to approach the problem
and we couldn't possibly test them all
so but take taking that step back
and looking at like what's all the
moving parts i guess obviously
you know the analogy doesn't involve
moving parts but it's like the
because i would never think to look at
that i would never think to look at
these things
but there is kind of a mindset in which
i would
if i knew to take guitar yeah like
breaking
because that pattern of every domino
covers a black and a white square
it doesn't like that doesn't appear
relevant at first
i think i think that the important part
to this is um to bring out the uh
algorithmic thinking and if you could
to me there's like a self-felt sense of
algorithmic thinking if i imagine doing
that
problem myself that way versus the
different
almost mind muscle i would sense into
where i was trying to
find an insight to a different way to
solve it
but it's the issue that we're zeroing in
on that that getting better
at breaking frame and finding the
relevant frame is something we want to
cultivate
with written r is that our goal right
now
just for for this meeting just
identifying that as the issue
no i was just sort of raising that idea
yeah so i i would i would
assert as a rule in the conversation
right where you first have to justify
the relevance of your frame
before you can adopt it
and then at least we we
keep back to the tangents because i
think
i i don't think it's so much an issue of
getting in the wrong frames getting lost
in the rabbit hole that's
the evil two
so what would that look like are you
speaking to my comments do you want me
to speak to the relevance of my comment
no no no i'm i'm just saying this as as
a rule right
if we want to improve the way this
conversation goes
or written our conversations in general
right like
it's it's it's useful to justify
what you're what you're planning to do
so that everybody's on the same page and
then we can first discuss the relevance
of the thing you're trying to do before
you're
you're trying to actually
lay out the whole plan
i'm not opposed to that in principle i
think some people may
balk at speaking if
they have to give that type of
justification um
so it's it's a pro and con uh
situation there do it if you can like do
it if you can i suppose
yeah i don't want to bar people from
introducing their ideas but it's it's
it's it's like an intention more so than
yeah setting the intention
well what is what is your intention
reframing for that statement
well so so what i see in this
conversation right there's there's a lot
of
humbling about from left to right and
and
what i want to do is be productive right
you
want to have a sense that we accomplish
something here and that we have all
learned something and
that therefore you need optimization and
this is i think a way
to have uh fruitful optimization
do you think that everyone is making the
same assessment as yourself with regards
to the value of the conversation
well i think he's proposing that i think
he's proposing that as
as a value we should adopt for the
conversation and he's putting that on
the table
no no i mean i'm asking him directly
about
his uh assessment of the overall
productivity
it it seems i mean i'm i'm willing to
grant that
i did i didn't make an assessment i said
i made a proposal for an optimization
and i'm i'm saying that things can be
better and if someone is going to
disagree with that then
yeah i don't i don't even
know how you'd have to allow for
disagreement right i mean
i'm i'm i'm not i'm not for closing on
this agreement
and i also said it's an
intention-setting thing it's not an
absolute rule because absolute rules are
sure so i would say if you're optimizing
for insight
jail i'm not sure if you're still
talking but we can't hear you
i'm the internet hater it's okay
yeah and i was just raising the question
of like how do we
and it probably merits spending a little
bit of time on just figuring out how we
and i think you have i'm sorry i missed
the first two meetings but just how do
we
how do we want to approach these like if
we're going through a video
how do we want to approach it is it just
identifying so we've identified for
example now
the issue of transframing and breaking
frame and getting better at
switching frames and identifying what's
relevant
is that as far as we want to go and now
we move on to
the next part or do we want to explore
more
for example how we would do that how do
we want to go
we can do how do we want to approach
this in this type of meeting
all right my suggestion would be
start off by talking about the video and
talking about
physics alien points and then trying to
tie those points back to root now and
tying them into okay how does this
relate to
this part of the project how does it
relate to that part of the project
uh and then if there are any um new
projects that arise
based on the video and based on the
discussion then looking
for okay is this part of another
existing project or
is this a new project and if so who's
willing to take it on
that's basically the idea
yeah what i was going to say was that i
think everybody will have their
their own um ideas with respect to
what's important in the in the videos
and so the idea was that people could
just take notes and then they would
bring they would share their notes
for discussion yeah
but you know what exactly the the no
cheering was supposed to achieve i guess
that wasn't considered well yeah so
the the idea was that we share notes
we're all going to notice different
information by sharing
we're probably going to you know get a
better
more full sense of what what the video
can offer
and then because we've recorded it we
can then take
notes and make it more permanent
on paper and then put it in the retina
document or something
i have to admit though it's actually
kind of difficult to take notes of these
videos because
um you know in many cases john is saying
the same things
to different audiences and so there's a
lot of repetition
and so you actually get used to a lot of
the things that have been said and you
don't really
notice them or think about them you know
to take notes
like i watched the whole video but i
ended up not wanting to write anything
down because i was like well
i've dealt with all of this you know
what is there really to discuss
and i don't i'm not sure if that's the
right attitude that you should have
towards this content or
if the you know the more familiar
retinal people will
have that experience i don't know but um
it's an unlikely possibility i guess
i definitely had some trouble putting
down
worthwhile notes but i guess this is the
value of the noobs
the newbies because they'll they'll see
it more freshly
yeah and come to think of it um if i'm
looking at the playlist i think it's
going to be very different
because that was a talk right the first
video was a conversation
so i think the conversations will will
actually be easier for note-taking
relative to the talks
we might even want to maybe just you
know like look at the list and maybe
consider beforehand
whether or not the video is even worth
considering uh worth talking about in
the first place
i don't know if i want to do that yeah
um
but then well i guess the question is
how do we go about doing that quality
control
i think it's it's fine just to go with
let's just go with conversations rather
than lectures
because i would bet that lectures are
probably generally just going to be
giving us
you know general stuff what we already
heard in other words
yeah yeah i think that's a reasonable
reason
anybody else got some ideas
and of course anybody else got any notes
they want to share
if you can't
i didn't do notes for this week but but
i i will in the future
well i mean we have been at this for 90
minutes so you know um
the entire video was only an hour
so yeah like what i might propose and
it doesn't have to be in in this time
slot
to instead of watching this stuff alone
in preparation organize a watching party
and
then you can just discuss it and take
notes together like it
i'm not saying don't do that but i like
the idea of us
being able to mull it over a little bit
for a few days before we
discuss it because we can there's
relevant ways things connect right
that you're not going to be able to just
come up with on the spot
what about you could have a watch party
before the conversation and then yeah
split those up
well also yeah there's nothing saying
you can't have watched it a few days
before the watch party yeah right the
watch party doesn't have to be a fresh
watch
it could be just a the platform for
bringing everything
up uh so watching these videos more than
once is
not a bad idea in any event so you can
do your yeah
and and you can have you can have
all all the talk right like getting up
to date on what's going
on around it right you can pause the
video and discuss
things in between all that stuff is is
possible
and then we we can segregate certain
types of conversation to that and then
have the meeting actually be a meeting
because i think that's
that's really important
so i guess like in light of what other
i want to kind of try to qualify my
previous statement which is that
the reason i brought up algorithmic
thinking was
referring to another point john made i'm
not sure if it was in this video a
different video
but that the algorithmic thinking is
non-convergent whereas heuristic
thinking is and that
um would there be a felt sense of that
and would that be part of written r
to be able to have a part of the
practice around trying to detect
these two versions of exemplified by the
chessboard
problem as a practice so
on that point i've been working on a
system
with mark and uh yeah i think that
system is based on that distinction
specifically
and we're gonna use that in order to
evaluate
the the ecology of practices so yeah i
think i think that's a really important
distinction
oh yeah just wanted to get this in uh i
don't think
i would actually be able to do a watch
party
because sometimes the sheer number of
people in the call alone
can break my internet and i've noticed
when i'm watching a stream or i've got
like webcams on that just guarantees
that it will break down
so if if we did that then i literally
wouldn't be able to come anymore
meaning even if you're not the one doing
the video
you can't watch any stream where we're
watching somebody else's
as far as i know
yeah so this is actually why i wanted to
separate the watch party from the actual
discussion
i think what should be two separate
events i i agree
and and there's a website you can use if
you don't want to use the stream and
it's like
watch together or whatever then you can
have everybody on the same
part of the video
yeah we can use watch together
that might be a way although the only
downside is if we're recording it
because
it might be interesting for people to
watch you know you know like commentary
videos
uh with the would it show up in the
stream too
i wonder if i could use obs
or something to have them both i don't
know
that's complicated
we don't have to put it on youtube be
nice
i don't know i think if you're if you're
doing a watch party then you're just
having
you know um spontaneous reactions it's
probably better not to record that kind
of thing
that's i don't know maybe i'm just well
i think i think people
often like watching commentary videos
and
and like the advantage
for a third party someone just watching
it on youtube is they get the advantage
of seeing the
the video part and then seeing the
commentary too so
it can be i don't know it might be worth
experimenting with to see if people like
like those videos in terms of spreading
what we're doing
well i mean there's no reason that you
couldn't have like a retinal watch party
that just does that anyway
yeah it doesn't have to be mandatory
right like it's it's just a way to make
community
and like if you want to watch it on your
own that's fine if you want to watch it
together that's
that's great as well right like it's
just more options more ways to engage
and i think that's always good
yeah the only objection is just
replacing
this format with that that's the only
problem no i i think it was the idea was
an advent
was in addition yeah yeah it i'm
i'm happy with an addition
so yeah i think we've uh basically
done with the whole discussion of the
video now so
recording can stop
all right thanks everyone so i will stop
it
now